{"tossups": [{"question": "Cynthia Ann Parker lived most of her life among this Native American group. Buffalo Hump, a leader of these people, led the Great Raid of 1840 after over thirty of their chieftains were massacred in the Council House Fight. The Kiowa, the Apache, and this group fought against American troops at the two battles of Adobe Walls, and they effectively controlled large parts of northern Mexico prior to the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this Native American group who were the foremost raiders of the Great Plains in the first half of the 19th century.", "answer": "<b> Comanche</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A prophetess tells this historical figure that he will be able to speak clearly in 1900 years; that occurs in a novel in which this figure catches a wounded wolf cub that is dropped from the sky by two feuding eagles. In Hell, this character is condemned to play dice with a bottomless box in a play by Seneca titled the<em> Apocolocyntosis</em>, or<em> Pumpkinification</em>, of this man. In a 1934 novel, this man uses his stutter to play the fool and avoid the schemes of Livia and Sejanus. For ten points, name this Roman emperor, the subject of a novel by Robert Graves titled<em> I, [this man]</em>.", "answer": "<b> Claudius</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "The Earl of Bothwell was imprisoned in a fortress in this city originally built by Eric of Pomerania; that fortress is now a museum complex. This city\u2019s formerly-industrial V\u00a8astra Hamnen neighborhood is now a gentrified neighborhood marked by Santiago Calatrava\u2019s Turning Torso residential skyscraper. This city in Scania, southwest of Lund, is the eastern terminus of an international bridge that passes the island of Saltholm. For ten points, name this city across the Oresund Bridge from Copenhagen in Sweden.", "answer": "<b> Malmo</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This historian\u2019s namesake law argues that disaster is far less common than various reports suggest. A book by this historian that is sometimes titled<em> Sand Against the Wind</em> examines the life of Joseph Stilwell in China. A discussion of the Little Ice Age opens another book by this historian that covers the \u201cCalamitous 14th Century.\u201d This historian is best known for a 1962 work whose \u201cOutbreak\u201d section details Franz Ferdinand\u2019s assassination. For ten points, name this female historian who wrote<em> A Distant</em> <em>Mirror</em> and<em> The Guns of August</em>.", "answer": "Barbara Wertheim<b> Tuchman</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man was the primary author of the Foraker Act, which laid the groundwork for civilian rule over Puerto Rico. This man, who served as the inaugural chairman of the Council on Foreign Relations, was succeeded as Secretary of War by William Howard Taft. In his highest post, this man maintained the Open Door policy of his predecessor, John Hay, by negotiating an agreement that limited the immigration of Japanese-Americans to California with Takahira Kogoro. For ten points, name this Secretary of State under Theodore Roosevelt and winner of the 1912 Nobel Peace Prize.", "answer": "Elihu<b> Root</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This event inspired Elton Simpson to participate in a similar attack on the Curtis Culwell Center in Texas. The perpetrators of this attack were killed during a gunfight in the Dammartin-en-Go\u00a8ele siege. A man who used the pen name Cabu was killed in this event, which was carried out by two brothers of Algerian descent in response to cartoons making fun of Mohammad. After this event, supporters of its target carried around signs reading \u201cJe suis [its cartoon mascot].\u201d For ten points, name this 2015 attack that targeted a newspaper office in Paris.", "answer": "<b> Charlie Hebdo</b> shooting (or attack, etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Marinetti claimed that this sculpture was not as beautiful as a racing car in the Futurist Manifesto, although futurist Umberto Boccioni used this sculpture\u2019s pose as a basis for his<em> Unique Forms of</em> <em>Continuity in Space</em>. This statue once stood on a stone reconstruction of a ship\u2019s prow, meant to celebrate a naval battle; it is now displayed atop the Daru Stairase in the Louvre. For ten points, name this headless Hellenistic sculpture of a female goddess with wings, found in 1863 on a namesake Greek island.", "answer": "Winged<b> Victory of Samothrace</b> (or<b> Nike of Samothrace</b>; prompt on Nike or Winged Victory)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "One member of this dynasty ordered Mohammed Pessian beheaded and his head displayed after he revolted against a coup that installed Ziaeddin Tabatabaee as Prime Minister. That member of this family was appointed head of a Cossack brigade by Edmund Ironside and was the father of a man who threw an elaborate party to celebrate 2,500 years of the Persian Empire. The Qajar dynasty was supplanted by, for ten points, what family that was overthrown in the 1979 Iranian Revolution?", "answer": "<b> Pahlavi</b> dynasty (accept (Mohammad) Reza Shah<b> Pahlavi</b>, but do not accept or prompt on Reza and/or Shah alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This group caused the second ever closing of Disneyland when it conquered Tom Sawyer Island and planted its New Nation flag. The founder of this group dressed in an American Revolutionary uniform and blew bubbles during a Congressional hearing. In 1976 this group nominated Nobody for President after earlier having promised to eat its eat its first candidate if he won; that candidate was Pigasus, a pig. Abbie Hoffman and Jerry Rubin were co-founders of, for ten points, what counter-cultural group of revolutionary pranksters behind the Youth International Party?", "answer": "<b> Yippie</b>s (accept<b> Youth International Party</b> or<b> YIP</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A leader of these people named Teodor helped lead the Uprising in Banat, in which relics of a saint were burnt. Saint Sava, a person of this ethnicity founded the monastery of Hilandar at Mount Athos. A knight of this ethnicity killed Murad II with a hidden dagger. The Battle of Maritsa was lost by these people, who have traditionally scorned modern scholarship and branded Vuk Brankovi\u00b4c as a traitor for his actions at the Battle of the Field of the Blackbirds, where Lazar led these people against the Ottomans. The Nemanji\u00b4c Dynasty ruled, for ten points, what Balkan people who now name a country with capital at Belgrade?", "answer": "<b> Serb</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Members of this ethnicity killed people on Richard Scott\u2019s ship, which was sending supplies to Fort Scott in retaliation for the Fowltown massacre. At the Negro Fort, Edmund Gaines attacked these people, who had committed the Dade Massacre. The execution of Robert Ambrister and Alexander Arbuthnot occurred in territory owned by this tribe. For ten points, name this Native American tribe that was twice by Andrew Jackson and led by Osceola in Florida.", "answer": "<b> Seminole</b>s (or<b> Mikisuki</b>s; prompt on Native Americans before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This state\u2019s creation was opposed by peasant brotherhoods like the Red Spear Society and the Big Swords Society. After this state captured Rehe, it signed the Tanggu Truce, creating a demilitarized zone to its south. A border dispute between this state and Soviet Mongolia erupted at the Battle of Khalkhin Gol. The Lytton Report denounced a staged explosion on a railway near Mukden that caused the invasion creating this state. Emperor Puyi was installed in, for ten points, what puppet state of Imperial Japan in northeast China?", "answer": "<b> Manchukuo</b> (accept<b> Japanese Manchuria</b>; accept<b> Manshu-koku</b>; prompt on Manchuria)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Constitution of 1791 distinguished between active and passive forms of this status. This status was extended to Algerian Jews in the Cr\u00b4emieux [creh-m\u2019yew] Decree. For ten points, name this status that can be acquired \u201cby spilled blood\u201d by soldiers wounded in the Foreign Legion, who can then vote in certain European elections.", "answer": "<b> French citizenship</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A prominent opponent of this practice toured Britain at the invitation of Catherine Impey. Thomas Moss became a victim this of practice after he opened the Peoples Grocery in a neighborhood nicknamed The Curve. The book<em> The Red Record</em> contained statistics about this practice and argued that many southerners used the \u201crape myth\u201d to justify it. Activist Ida Wells campaigned against this practice, the subject of \u201cStrange Fruit\u201d by Billie Holliday. For ten points, name this vigilante crime in which African Americans where hanged.", "answer": "<b> lynch</b>ing (accept word forms; prompt on killing, execution, and other generic terms)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A character in this work proclaims that \u201call travel is a penance now;\u201d that character has this opera\u2019s final aria, in which he asks \u201chow much of what we did was good?\u201d from his bed. This opera opens with a recitation of the \u201cThree Rules of Discipline and Eight Points for Attention.\u201d The title character states that \u201cthe eyes and ears of the world were listening\u201d in the aria \u201cNews has a kind of mystery,\u201d which he sings after stepping off the<em> Spirit of \u201876</em> to meet Premier Chou En-Lai. For ten points, name this John Adams opera that depicts a 1972 summit between Mao Zedong and the title U.S. president.", "answer": "<b> Nixon in China</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This document\u2019s author said that its signatories were drawn more to C. Wright Mills\u2019</b><em><b>The Power Elite</b></em><b> than to Marx, Lenin or Trotsky.\u201d The Student Afro Society and the group</b> <b>that authored this document shut Columbia University down during the (+)</b> <b>\u201cTen Days</b> <b>of Resistance.\u201d This document, which claims to \u201cseek the unattainable\u201d to \u201cavoid the unimaginable,\u201d begins \u201cWe are people of this generation, (*)</b> bred in at least modest comfort, housed now in universities, looking uncomfortably to the world we inherit.\u201d For ten points, name this founding document of the Students for a Democratic Society.", "answer": "<b> Port Huron</b> Statement", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>After 1763, this function was overseen by the Lieutenant General of the Police in France, where this function had been liberally overseen by Lamoignon de Malesherbes [la-mwa-n\u2019yon de mal-shairb]. Voltaire sparked a wave of Anglophilia by celebrating England\u2019s relative</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>lack of this function, which was lessened by the increased use of tacit permissions.</b> <b>Amsterdam was a center for those escaping this action, which sought to restrict calumny and (*)</b> protect religion and morality. The<em> Encyclopedie</em> was a target of, for ten points, what government action that controls print material?", "answer": "<b> censor</b>ship (accept word forms)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In a letter to Pope Pius IX [ninth], a leader of this country noted that Masonic Lodges,\u201cinstigated by Germany, are vomiting against me all sorts of atrocious insults and horrible columnities;\u201d that leader of this country predicted his own assassination, which came by machete at the hands of Faustin Rayo. Another President of this nation led its (+) Liberal Revolution of 1895. Gabriel Garcia Moreno and Eloy Alfaro were leaders of this country, where Mechor Aymerich lost an 1822 battle to Antonio Jos\u00b4e de Sucre on the slopes of the (*) </b> Pichincha Volcano. Jos\u00b4e de San Martin met Sim\u00b4on Bol\u00b4\u0131var in, for ten points, what country that hosted the Guayaquil Conference and, in Spanish rule, included the autonomous Real Audiencia de Quito?", "answer": "<b> Ecuador</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A character in this film asks if eating oysters is moral and eating snails immoral. This film\u2019s opening narration speaks of a city \u201cfatally stricken\u201d with \u201chuman slavery\u201d that is</b> <b>destined to fall to Christianity. John F. Kennedy crossed a (+)</b> <b>picket line to view this</b> <b>Stanley Kubrick film, whose screenwriter, Dalton Trumbo, had been blacklisted as a member of the Hollywood 10. When asked to identify their leader, (*) </b> rebels in this film rise to their feet and claim \u201cI am\u201d the title character. For ten points, name this 1960 film about the title gladiator\u2019s fight against the Roman Republic.", "answer": "<b> Spartacus</b> ", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "<b>This man ordered Quintus Cerialis to put down the Batavi revolt. After the Battle of Yodfat, the future historian Josephus became a slave to this man. This emperor</b> <b>ordered that the Colossus of Nero be (+)</b> <b>converted into a statue of Sol, and he</b> <b>ordered an infamous urine tax. Agricola was sent to annex Britain during this man\u2019s reign. This Roman emperor, who (*) </b> started construction on the Coliseum, took power at the end of the Year of the Four Emperors. For ten points, name this founder of the Flavian Dynasty and father of Titus and Domitian.", "answer": "<b> Vespasian</b> (accept Titus Flavius Caesar<b> Vespasian</b>us Augustus)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "icotencatl [she-co-ten-cah-tell] the Younger led this Mexican city, which allied with Cortes against the Aztecs.", "answer": "<b> Tlaxcala</b>n [t\u2019lahsh-ca-la] Page 13", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}